Guide to the Kaercher and Packer family papers,1789-1938.
Kaercher and Packer family papers
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Kaercher and Packer family papers, 1789-1938.
347
Kaercher family.
2.5 cubic ft; 4 v.; 2 museum folders.
Correspondence, commissions, reports, licenses, financial accounts, sermons, deeds, agreements, veterinary formulas, diaries, essays, poetry, and other items.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Correspondence and other papers relating the life of George Kaercher, who was a divinity student at Burr Seminary in Manchester, Vermont and Western Reserve College in Ohio, and later a minister in Ohio. Also includes papers of the Packer family.
BIOGRAPHICAL NOTE
George Kaercher was a divinity student at Burr Seminary, Manchester, Vermont, and Western Reserve, Ohio and a minister in Ohio.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Letters to Kaercher commenting on education, economic and social conditions, the costs of travel, revivals among students and laymen, Taylorism (New Haven theology), Millerism (Millerite movement), the need of ministers among German immigrants of Ohio and Pennsylvania, the American Tract Society, religion on the frontier, epidemics, the Reverend Albert Barnes, Dr. Tyng, and other divines; commissions and reports to the American Home Missionary Society, licenses to preach, accounts as to expenses and salaries; correspondence of Rev. Kaercher during the Civil War with the Woman's Central Association of Relief, sermons, and a few Anti-Masonic and Anti-Slavery items. Also, Packer family papers, including deeds, agreements, accounts, receipts, personal and business correspondence of the Packer, Mason, and Kaercher families; veterinary formulas of Johnathan Packer; includes diaries, essays, poetry, and miscellanea. Families are centered in Preston, Chenango County, New York.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Kaercher family.; Barnes, Albert.; Kaercher, George.; Mason family.; Packer family.; Packer, Johnathan.; American Home Missionary Society.; American Tract Society.; Burr Seminary.; Western Reserve College.; Woman's Central Association of Relief.
Subjects:
Theological seminaries.; Family--New York (State)--Preston.; Freemasonry.; Antislavery movements.; Millerite movement.; New Haven theology.; Immigrants.; Revivals.; Veterinary drugs.; Clergy.
Places:
Chenango County (N.Y.)--Economic conditions.; Chenango County (N.Y.)--Social conditions.; Chenango County (N.Y.)--Religious life and customs.
Form and Genre Terms:
Sermons.; Diaries.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
CONTAINER LIST
- B, Woodruff and Packer. Deeds, letters, account, receipts, 1789-1912 and no date. (Box 1)
- A 4-5, Sermons of Rev. George Kaercher. (Box 2)
- A 1-3, Kaercher papers.
  - 1 religious poem written in German - 1816 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - 1 letter - May 8, 1838 - John W. Elliot to George Kaercher - from Manual Labor Inst., Marion, Ala. - lack of educational advantages in South - opportunity for "enterprising merchant, mechanic, or professional man" (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - 2 letters - Feb. 12 and Dec. 13, 1834 - from Williams College - Oliver M. Sears to Kaercher - college life, religious excitement, aid for those studying for the ministry at Williams (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - 1 letter - 1839 - Hudson, Ohio - unsigned to Kaercher - costs of going from Albany to Ohio, living costs at Western Reserve, etc. - idea of Kaercher laboring among own people in West - muddy roads in Ohio - Prof. St. John and collection of mineral specimens (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - 1 letter - Oct. 1839 - to Kaercher - received $15 aid from American Education Society while at Burr Seminary (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - 1 pledge - Nov. 1839, Manchester, Vt. - by students to pray, on separation, for each member of group for one year (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - 1 letter - Dec. 16, 1839 - Western Reserve - Jacob Patch to Kaercher - division of church in Sharon - religious schism - division among congregations of churches - urges Kaercher to bring whole class with him to Western Reserve - college literary societies (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - 1 letter - Feb. 25, 1840 - Watertown - Guernsey to Kaercher - religious revival - sermons of M. Grovsnor (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Expenses at Burr Seminary - Mar. 25, 1840 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Receipt for work - July 4, 1841 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - 1 letter - July 27, 1840 - Amenia - Hiram Weed to Kaercher - on aid from home people to Kaercher - hard times - furnaces (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - 1 letter - July 9, 1840 - Upton, Mass. - M. Grosvenor conducting good revival in region (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - 1 letter - Oct. 10, 1840 - Burr Seminary - uses shorthand - epidemic (?) - many deaths (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - 1 letter - Mar. 13, 1841 - Manchester (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - 1 letter - Mar. 28, 1841 - Aaron Read to Kaercher urging him to sing in gallery in church, not to leave it, that singing before long will be from front of pulpit (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - 1 letter - July 31, 1841 - S.N. Grant to Kaercher - Storatton - Kaercher has been helping to conduct revivals - state of Burr Seminary - 4th July celebration at Townsend (3 or 400,000 present) (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - 1 letter - May 6, 1842 - Manchester - Grant - condition of Burr Seminary - no religious revival, revival at Williams College (only 20 students there impenitent) (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - 1 letter - Apr. 25, 1843 - Sharon - Hiram Weed to Kaercher - Presbyterians and revival - (Methodists influenced by Millerism) - Christ to come this month - not many to believe this part "yet the multitude that came to hear from curiosity were willing to attend from night to night that they might hear the truth from Mr. Reed and others" (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - 1 letter - June 9, 1843 - Savanah - Christine Carlen to Kaercher at Western Reserve - husband (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - 1 letter - Oct. 1, 1843 - Sharon - Hiram Weed - Post Office creates excitement - revival died down (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - 1 letter - Oct. 24, 1843 - Detroit - Lucious C. Rouse - had proposed to American Tract Society that Kaercher work during vacation in Stack Co. - ATS refused, wanting permanent works - Rouse urges Kaercher to preach to Germans in Ohio or Penn. and consult with German Reformed or Presbyterians Church - number of Germans in Springfield and Canton - urges Kaercher to spend vacation in exploration trip among these Germans and in giving away tracts (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - 1 citizenship papers - George Kaercher - May 21, 1844, Akron, Ohio (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - 1 licence to preach - July 24, 1844 - Hudson - G. Kaercher - by Presbytery of Portage (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - 1 letter - Oct. 21, 1844 - Yale - Guernsey to G. Kaercher (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - 1 commission from Home Missionary Society - Dec. 21, 1844 - G. Kaercher - six months at Northampton, Summit Co., Ohio - to receive $25 and rent from congregation (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - 1 letter - Mar. 14, 1845 - Guernsey to Kaercher - Kaercher's brother Frederick arrested for counterfeiting money (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - 1 letter - Aug. 4, 1845 - Guernsey to Kaercher - description of Albert Barnes, Stephen Higginson, Dr. Tying (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - 1 diploma - Aug. 14, 1845 - G. Kaercher - Western Reserve College (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - 1 commission from Home Missionary Society - Sept. 1, 1845 - 1 year at Peninsula - $100 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - 1 letter - Oct. 22, 1845 - Yale - Guernsey to Kaercher - New School Presbyterian Church at Newburgh, N.Y. (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - 1 letter - Nov. 20, 1845 - Lima, Mich. - E.P. Marvin - on advantages of minister's life (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - 1 license - Nov. 24, 1845 - State of Ohio - to Kaercher to perform marriages (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - 1 letter - Jan. 20, 1846 - Yale - Blakeslee to Kaercher - likes Wm. Taylor as lecturer but condemns Taylorism (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - 1 letter - Jan. 26, 1846 - Wolcottville, Conn. - theory of annihilation of the wicked - on salaries (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - 1 letter - July 7, 1846 - New Haven - Blakeslee - Westerner by birth, nothing would keep him in East - influence of Reserve in Ohio, on Lakes and Mississippi Valley - "For the people of the Reserve have the intelligence and enterprise of North East combined with the energy and go-a-headativeness of the West" (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - 1 letter - Aug. 24, 1846 - Knoxville, Knox Co., Ill. - R.C. Bristol to Kaercher - describes state of churches (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - 1 commission - Sept. 1, 1846 - G. Kaercher - 1 year at Peninsula, Ohio, for $100 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - 1 quarterly report to American Home Missionary Society - Dec. 11, 1846 - Peninsula - G. Kaercher - Methodists held protracted meeting - quite a lot of sickness (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - 1 letter - Mar. 8, 1847 - H.K. Smith to Kaercher - formation of a Teacher's Institute for schoolteachers (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - 1 letter - Dec. 28, 1846 - Northampton - R.C. Bristol - preached in bar using bar for pulpit (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - 1 quarterly report to AHM - asks for leave to visit sick mother - June 9, 1847 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - 1 letter - July 26, 1847 - R.C. Bristol - urges Kaercher to come to Illinois - great need for ministers (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - 1 commission - Nov. 1, 1849 - G. Kaercher - Peninsula - 1 year - $75 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - 1 letter - June 21, 1848 - Henry Reid to Kaercher - presents plan for him to come to Waterville and preach half the time and spend half under the direction of American Tract Society (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Additional papers (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - 3 letters - 1850
    - Hiram Weed to G. Kaercher - Sharon (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Joel Case to G. Kaercher - Victoria, Tex. (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Eunice Ford to G. Kaercher (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - 3 letters - 1851
    - S. Wright to G. Kaercher - New Berlin (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Charles Cunty to G. Kaercher - Peninsula (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Aaron Reed to G. Kaercher - Sharon (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - 1 commission - 1851 - to G. Kaercher - Preston - 1 yr. 50 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - 1 petition - 1851 - to American Home Missionary Society for payment of $50 to Kaercher - congregation to pay $200 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - 3 letters - 1852
    - Catherine Kaercher to G. Kaercher - father (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Catherine Kaercher to G. Kaercher - father (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Eunice Ford to G. Kaercher (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - 2 letters - 1854
    - George and Cornelia Kaercher to Lucy Packer (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Lucy Packer to George and Cornelia Kaercher (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - 5 letters - 1854 - George Kaercher to his wife, Cornelia (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - 1 letter - 1855 - Catherine Kaercher to G. Kaercher (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Additional papers (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - 1 letter - 1856 - G. Kaercher to nephew - Preston (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - 4 letters - 1857
    - Wm. Potter to G. Kaercher - Claridon (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - G.W. Roberts to G. Kaercher - Green, N.Y. (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - H.W. Gilbert to G. Kaercher - Green, N.Y. (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - J. Patch to G. Kaercher - Orland, Ind. (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - 4 letters - 1858
    - J. Patch to G. Kaercher - Orland, Ind. (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Ellen to Cornelia Kaercher - Cleveland (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Edward Baymal to G. Kaercher - concerning death of Kaercher's sister, Catherine Baymal, and son (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - C.A. Hernandes to G. Kaercher - Savannah - concerning death of Kaercher's sister (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - 2 letters - 1859
    - G. Kaercher to his wife - Tabery (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - G. Kaercher to nephew - Preston (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - 2 letters - 1862 - Woman's Central Ass. of Relief to G. Kaercher (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - 8 letters to G. Kaercher from Elisabeth Wilbur and children (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - 5 letters - 1864
    - Mary Fairbanks to Cornelia Kaercher (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - S. Wait to G. Kaercher - Four Mill Grove (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - J.K. Mason to G. Kaercher (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - 2 letters - G. Kaercher to his mother - Sharon (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - 4 letters - 1866
    - Sharon - George Wilbur - to G. Kaercher (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Tomah - F. Ebert to G. Kaercher (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Tomah - Daniel Ebert to G. Kaercher (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Pottsville - George Kaercher to George Kaercher (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - 4 letters - 1868
    - Catherine Field to G. Kaercher - Trempealeau (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Charles A. Throop to G. Kaercher - Trempealeau (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - James A. Throop to G. Kaercher - Trempealeau (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Helen Noyes to Cornelia Kaercher (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - 2 letters - 1869
    - Daniel Ebert to G. Kaercher (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Aaron Reed to G. Kaercher (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - 2 letters - 1874
    - Daniel Ebert to G. Kaercher (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - D. Vrooman to G. Kaercher (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - 2 letters - 1878 - G. Kaercher to family (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - 3 letters - Mary Fairbanks to Cornelia Kaercher - Barnabas Horves Jr. to George Kaercher (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Constitution of the Social and Benevolent Society of the Town of Preston (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Report of number of bibles in families of church (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - List of subscribers for benefit of George Kaercher (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - 8 miscellaneous pieces (Box 3, Folder 7)
- B, Woodruff and Packer. Justice of the Peace records, elections records, etc., Preston, NY, 1817-1890 and no date. (Box 4)
- Mss., diries of Kaercher, Mason, Noyes, and Packer families, 1817-1922 and no date. (Box 4)
- Volumes, assessment book, 1848; genealogical information on Beaumont, Mason, Packer, Pratt, Woodruff and other families, 1764-1940. (Box 5)
- Scrapbooks, copybooks, 1836-1913 and no date. Also list of voters Town of Preston, Oct. 13, 1863; "The German Church Friend for American German Churches," Jan.-Dec. 1850, 11 issues. (Box 6)
- Photographs. (Box 7)
- Misc. printed material on Centennial Exhibition, Philadelphia, Pa., 1876, souvenir item. (Box 7)
- Four loose mss. vols. (Volume 1-4)